Cool.
Hello, everyone.
And welcome to
Lecture 5 of CME295.
So first of all, thank you
all for taking the time
to take the midterm last week.
So I hope it was
reasonable for you.
So for those of you
who are auditing,
in case you are interested
in taking the exam,
just know that the
exam and the solutions
are both posted on the website.
And so now, you know a little
bit how the exam looks like.
So for the final, we'll
have the same format,
except that the content will
be on lectures 5, so this one,
up until 9.
So all good on that point?
Cool.
Great.
So with that, we're going
to start the lecture.
So today, we're going to
talk about LLM tuning.
So as usual, we're just going
to recap what we saw last time.
So last time was
already two weeks ago.
But we talked about
how to train an LLM.
And in particular, we've
looked at two important steps.
So the first one was
called pre-training,
where you're basically taking a
model that has been initialized,
and you're trying to teach
the model about language,
about code.
So you have this step
that is very time
consuming, expensive,
compute heavy, that
is happening on a lot of data.
So we've seen
training optimizations
on how to make that happen.
So we've seen techniques to
parallelize that across GPUs.
So we've seen data parallelism
methods and, in particular, 0.
So the variant 0, 1, 2, 3.
And we've also seen very quickly
what model parallelism was
in this case.
So at the end of
this step, what you
obtain is a model that knows
about the structure of language,
about codes--
basically, all the texts
that it has been fed.
But what this model can do is
only predict the next token.
So it's a great autocompleter,
but it's not a helpful model
yet, which is why we
have a second step.
And we saw here, it's typically
called finetuning or SFT
for Supervised Fine Tuning.
So here what we do is we
take our pre-trained model,
and we train it
for specific tasks.
So nowadays, you have ChatGPT
and all these chat assistants.
So this can be one application.
So transforming your
model into an assistant.
And so here, the goal is to
teach the model how to behave.
So the model already
knows what language
is, what code is, et cetera.
And you're just trying to make
it behave like the use case
that you're trying
to tune it for.
So typically here,
what you have is
a data set that is
much smaller in scale,
but of much higher quality.
And you're basically taking your
model, your pre-trained model,
and teaching it
exactly which tokens
to predict with the next
token prediction task.
And we've seen, LoRA, which is
a parameter efficient method,
which does not tune all the
weights, but in a clever way,
introduces low rank
matrices that are
the ones that are being tuned.
And we had stopped there.
So what we're going
to see today is
how to align the model to
align with, what we call,
human preferences.
And so here, we're
taking our model
that has been finetuned
for a specific task.
And trying to align
our model to make
it more something that
a human would like
or that some metric
that we're defining
would be more aligned with that.
So as an example, let's suppose
if you have an assistant
at the end step 2.
So it's very much possible
that your assistant
is behaving the way you want,
but not, let's say, at the tone
that you want.
So it's not, let's say,
friendly or it's not safe.
So you want to tune those
aspects in that third step.
Cool.
So this step is called
preference tuning.
And we're going to
exactly see what that is.
So here for context,
let's suppose
that we have an SFT model.
And so by SFT model,
I mean a model
that has gone through
the pre-trained stage
and the finetuning stage.
And so for instance,
we may ask our model
to suggest a new activity we
could do with our teddy bear.
And here the model,
let's say, responds with,
"I would suggest you to not
spend much time with your teddy
bear at all."
So this is the response
of an assistant,
but it's not necessarily
aligned with what we want.
So the idea here is to
take these, quote unquote,
"bad outputs" and find an output
or rewrite an output that we
would want to have instead.
So this pair would be what
we call a preference pair.
So in other words, given this
prompt, we have two responses--
one that we want to
see, which is this one.
And I'm going to
read it in a second.
And then the other one
that we do not want to see.
So for instance,
in this example,
the answer we want to
see is, "Of course,
teddy bears not only
make awesome companions
for a delightful sleep, but can
also be great buddies for fun
activities," and just like
suggest some activities.
Does the setup sound good?
Yeah?
So long story short, we
want to align our model
with human preferences.
So you may ask, we have this
finetuning step already.
Why would we want to
have a third step?
Well, during the second step,
which is the finetuning stage,
if you remember, what we did was
construct a very high quality
data set of the kinds of prompts
on which we want our model
to behave in a certain way.
So in order to compose
such a data set,
it's actually something that
is very time consuming and very
actually difficult,
because the data set must
be of very high quality.
And in this case,
what we're doing
is not really teaching the model
exactly what it should generate,
but rather telling the
model what kind of output
it should prefer.
So we're less in
"please generate that"
kind of thing and more
a "I prefer this option"
kind of thing.
And so typically, if we
asked you write a poem,
write a great poem
from scratch, it
would typically be much more
difficult to do rather than just
showing you two poems, one
bad poem and one great poem,
and ask you to just say
which one is better.
So in order to obtain the data
sets, it's already much easier.
The second reason is--
so during the SFT stage,
when we compose our data set
of very high quality,
there is one aspect
that we really try
to get right, which
is the distribution of prompts.
And what I mean by that is if
we have too much of a given
of prompt, our model
will be more biased
towards responding in
that particular way.
So what people
try to do is to be
careful about the
distribution of prompts that
are in the SFT data.
And so here, let's say
if our model misbehaves,
if we were thinking about just
adding one example in the SFT
data set, well, we would have
to be very careful about which
prompt we're adding
and whether it's not
going to bias the model like
too much in that direction.
So that's the second reason.
And then, the third
reason is what
I mentioned, which is
the SFT data is typically
very high quality.
So if you're looking
at all the missteps
that your model is
doing and trying
to put that in the SFT data,
you'll just have a hard time.
It takes a lot of time.
But one note here is if your
SFT data is misbehaving a lot,
it may also be due to the
fact that your SFT data
set has some problem.
So preference tuning is not
the answer to everything.
Maybe it's better sometimes to
just check your SFT data set
for some issues.
Does that sound good?
Yeah.
[AUDIO OUT]
Yeah, so to do that in the
preference tuning stage?
OK, so the question
is, we saw LoRA
for SFT, what is the equivalent
for preference tuning?
So we'll see that
later in the lecture.
But you can think of LoRA as
being some way to, I guess,
reduce the number of parameters
that you need to tune.
That is slightly different
with the objective function
that you're using
to train your model.
And here, preference
tuning, you can think of it
more as a different
objective function,
but it may very
well be something
that you also use LoRA for.
So the two are not incompatible.
But it will become
more clear later on.
But yeah, great question.
One last thing I will add
here is another difference
with the SFT stage is that
preference tuning allows us
to inject some negative signal.
Because SFT is all about
teaching the model about what
it should predict,
but it does not
teach the model about what
it should not predict.
And we will see that
preference tuning allows you
to inject some negative signal.
Cool.
So to start, of course, we need
to have our preference pairs.
And so we're going to look at
this data collection step first.
So here's the setup.
You have a prompt.
Let's say write a poem.
And you have a given
response, which
is the poem that is being
generated by the model.
You have a few ways to
construct your preference data.
So either you start with
a pointwise mindset,
where you score
each proposed poem
with some kind of
pointwise score,
and here pointwise
score means a score
just relative to
one observation.
You could very well do that, but
I will say it's kind of hard.
It's kind of tough as
a human to say, OK,
this one is, I
don't know, a 0.9.
This one is like a 0.2.
It's not super clear exactly
how you would scale that.
The second idea is for you to
get two observations at the time
and for you to say
which one is better.
So this one is called
pairwise preference data.
And it's much easier.
And then, the third
one is listwise,
which is get a list
of, let's say, n poems,
and then you just rank
which one is best, which one
is worst, et cetera, et cetera.
And I guess this one is
easier than pointwise,
because you don't have
to specify, I guess,
how much better it is,
but I guess it's still
a bit more complicated.
And that's the reason why
people typically use pairwise.
So what they do is they collect
pairwise preference data.
Meaning for each prompt, they
have two possible answers,
and then they just specify
which one is better.
And so that's the one we'll
continue this lecture with.
OK, so now you may ask, OK,
great, pairwise preference data.
But how do you get it?
Well, here is the recipe.
So in order to generate
a pair of responses--
so first, you need a prompt.
And we've seen-- previously, I
think it's in lecture probably
3--
that what you could do was
to generate different answers
if you have a temperature
that's positive.
So typically, what people
do is they put this prompt,
let's say, twice into the model
with a positive temperature,
and then they can get
two different answers.
The prompt is
typically something
where we wanted to follow
the distribution of what
the users typically ask.
So the prompt x can be something
that we obtain from the logs
or from, let's say, a
desired set of prompts.
And then what we do is we
have these two observations.
So the first one is the
prompt and the first response.
The second one is the prompt
and the second response.
And what we do is we rate--
we compare them.
So we can compare them with,
of course, human ratings.
But we can also compare them
with some other metrics.
So I'll just list a few.
So we have LLM as a judge,
which you may have heard of,
which we have not
seen yet, which
we will see in a few lectures
that is also typically used
to just compare, I guess, how
much better one observation is
compared to another.
We can also use some other
metrics, rule-based one
like BLEU, ROUGE, et
cetera, although, it
is not as used these days.
And the simplest way to compare
these two observations is
to have a binary
setting, where you say,
OK, is response 1 better
or worse than response 2?
But you could also think
of a more nuanced scale,
meaning you can also
say, OK, response
1 is much better, better,
slightly better, slightly
worse, worse, or much worse.
So this is also something
that you can do.
But there are some challenges
with that approach.
Because for instance,
if you, I don't know,
consider human
ratings, a lot of tasks
are a little bit subjective.
So in a lot of cases,
actually, what people do
is having a pairwise preference
data set on the binary scale.
So only is it better or worse.
Does that sound good?
Yeah.
OK, so another way to obtain
that data is to have--
to find in your logs a
response that you did not
like to take that response
and to rewrite it,
which is basically
what we did here.
So here, when we have the
response here, what we did
is take the response
and rewrite a good one.
So this is also what people do.
But of course, it is
a bit more involved,
because you need to generate.
And I told you that generation
was kind of costly and tough,
but this is also possible.
Does the data
collection make sense?
Yeah?
Cool.
OK, so now, we have
our preference data.
And what we want is to align our
model to prefer responses that
were preferred by the
rating, and, I guess,
down weight the responses
that were not preferred.
And so in order to
do that, we will see
a method that's called RLHF.
RLHF.
And I'll see-- we'll see that
in more details in a second.
But as the name indicates,
RLHF relies on RL.
So I'm just going to
start with some RL basics.
So do we have any
RL experts here?
Yeah?
No?
[CHUCKLES] So no need
to be an RL expert.
So don't worry.
We'll go really slowly on that.
So in the RL world, what people
do is they have an agent--
and here, I mean the
agent in RL term--
which interacts
with an environment.
So what does it do?
It is at a given state,
at, let's say, time t,
it can take an action at time t.
And it takes that action
according to some policy.
The policy is typically
denoted pi, pi of theta
of the action given the state.
So what that policy
means is simply
giving you the
probability of you
taking an action given a state.
Easy, right?
And so given that the
agent takes some action,
it also receives some rewards.
So sometimes, it's
a good reward.
Sometimes, it's bad rewards.
So what we're going
to do is to leverage
that mindset for our
preference tuning exercise.
So let's see together how we
can transpose these quantities
in the LLM world.
So what is the agent?
The agent is the LLM.
So in terms of the
state that it is in,
so it's simply the input
that it has so far.
So the action that it wants to
do is to predict the next token.
So it basically
always wonders, OK,
what is the next token
given this input?
And this action
or this next token
is among the set of
tokens that are out there.
So if you want--
the environment can be the set
of tokens of your vocabulary.
And in order to decide which
token should come next,
the LLM determines that using
the probability of next token,
which is obtained by when
you do your forward pass,
and when you look at the
probability distribution
as an output, which is
basically our policy.
So our policy here is
simply equal to the output
of the LLM given
the input in order
to determine the next token.
So far, so good?
And now, we're adding
one additional thing.
So I told you we're composing
our preference data sets.
And we want to know which output
is better than the other output.
And so we're going to
use that for our reward.
We're going to somehow
And we'll see how
we will use that.
So I'm going to just
recap that part.
So we have our LLM
take some input,
and then it wants to
predict the next token.
It wants to take this action.
So in order to do that, it uses
the probability distribution
that it outputs.
And then, the token
that it predicts
or the output that
it generates then
receives some reward that
is going to feed back
into tuning the agent.
And here is the LLM.
Yep.
[AUDIO OUT]
So the question is,
wouldn't that be expensive
if we do this for all pairs?
Why would that be expensive?
[AUDIO OUT]
Mm-hmm.
Yeah, so--
[AUDIO OUT]
Yeah, the question is, what do
you do in terms of how expensive
that is?
So yeah, typically, people
take batches, for instance.
But I would not--
so it is indeed expensive.
But we're going to see a little
bit some order of magnitude
and how that works.
But you can think of this
as being kind of a training
procedure that could be seen as
expensive as some other training
procedure.
There's nothing that
makes this more expensive,
but we're going to see exactly.
So I think there are some points
that you're touching correctly.
There are some parts
that are added compared
to the regular
supervised-- let's say,
supervised fine tuning setting.
And we're going to
see that in a second.
[AUDIO OUT]
So the question is, does
the reward that you're
getting from here, I guess,
powerful enough for the LLM
to change?
Well, you will see
some expressions
on the internet just
characterizing this training
procedure as it's nearly
not as many signals
as what you would get
for SFT, let's say.
But because for SFT,
you're literally
always taking a partial input
and making the LLM learn
how to generate the next token.
But here, you're only
getting roughly one signal
per completion.
So yeah, definitely
it's more sparse.
And that's why you
will see that RLHF
is seen as more an approach
that has sparse signals.
Yeah, yep.
[AUDIO OUT]
Great question.
So the question is, do you
apply a reward for each token
or for the whole thing?
We're going to see
this in more detail,
but it's for the whole thing.
It's for the whole thing.
But we'll see that
in just a second.
Yep.
[AUDIO OUT]
So the AD and--
oh, right, so the question
is, what is the AT and ST.
So just as a reminder, ST
is the state that you're in,
and AT is the action
you want to take.
So in the context of an LLM, the
state that you're in for an LLM
is the input that
you have so far.
And then the action is
which token you want
to generate given that input.
Yep.
Cool.
Yeah, so far so good?
OK, perfect.
So now that we know a little
bit what a mental model could
be for, I guess,
LLM-based RL, I just
want to highlight once more that
what we're trying to achieve
is learn how to align
this policy with rewards.
So we want to learn
theta, and theta
is the parameters of our LLM,
such that pi of theta aligns
with preferences.
And that's where
RLHF comes into play.
So RLHF stands for Reinforcement
Learning from Human Feedback.
And it is typically
composed of two stages.
So the first stage
is you figuring out
how to distinguish good
output from bad output.
So here, all the preference
pairs that you collected
are actually used for you to
learn what is good, what is bad.
So the input here
is the concatenation
of the prompt and the response.
And the output is a score.
So what you want to know given
a prompt and the response, how
good that is.
And then the second step is
the RL step, the Reinforcement
Learning step.
And this is where you use the
rewards to align your model
with the preferences.
So here as input,
you have the prompts.
And what you somehow
want to do is
to be able to generate
y hat that is more
aligned with the rewards.
And by the way, I just
want to call out one thing.
So RLHF is Reinforcement
Learning from Human Feedback.
The Human Feedback part
refers to the labels on which
the reward model is trained.
So if there are preference pairs
are based on human ratings,
then we're relying on human
preferences, then we're in RLHF.
Because you will see out there,
there is also RL, let's say,
AIF, a Reinforcement
Learning from AI Feedback.
And that one is relying
on non-human preferences.
So yeah.
Cool.
OK, so now that we know
what RLHF is and we
know that there are two steps,
we'll go through the first step
naturally.
So here the idea is
we want to construct
a model that knows which output
is good, which output is bad.
And of course,
here, what we want
is to not only consider the
output, but also the input,
because you need to somehow
contextualize that answer.
So let's go with our
favorite example.
So let's suppose you have
the following prompt.
Suggest a new activity I
could do with my teddy bear.
So what you want is to have a
reward model that-- here, we
note RM, --that tells you that
the answer that we rewrote
into the good answer is good.
And we want to somehow have
that model that tells us
that the output that
we constructed--
or that we did not construct,
the output that we saw was bad
is bad.
So we want to somehow
have a model that
takes in the prompts and the
good response and say it's good.
And we want to somehow
have a model that
takes the prompt and the bad
response to say it's bad.
So now the question is, how
do you construct such a model?
Well, in order to
do that, we are
using a formulation
that's called
the Bradley-Terry formulation.
So that one is an
important formula.
So we'll just stay
here for a little bit.
So what it says is that the
probability-- bless you--
to have an output yi be
better than an output yj is
equal to an exponential
of some score, which
is a score with
respect to i over
the exponential of that
score with respect to i
plus the exponential of some
score with respect to j.
So that is called the
Bradley-Terry formulation.
And this is the formulation we
will use to build our model.
So here, it's also equal
to sigma of ri minus rj.
So who knows what sigma is?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes, exactly.
So it's a sigmoid.
So just as a reminder
sigmoid is 1 over 1
plus exponential of minus x.
So this is how the
graph looks like.
So when it's minus infinity,
it tends towards 0,
and then towards plus
infinity, it tends towards 1.
So in other words, if i is
better than j, what we want
is for the input to sigma
to be as high as possible,
because you want the
probability to be as close to 1.
So you want to somehow have ri
be high if the output i is good
and somehow rj to be low,
if the output is bad.
So far so good?
So here, what we want to
do is to somehow train
a model that is able to
output scores ri and rj
using this formulation.
So this formulation
involves two quantities,
because we have a
pairwise data set.
So far so good?
So it will become more
clear in a second.
So here for training,
the idea here
is you have some model
that you initialize,
and you input on the one hand
your prompt x and your winning
output.
So I'm saying winning,
so it's y hat w.
You put it into the model.
It produces score
r of x and y hat w.
And then, you have a second
output, so x and yl, y hat l,
which is the losing output.
So you put it into the model,
and it has a second score.
And now, you somehow want to
have a loss function that takes
into account these two scores.
So based on this
formulation, do you
have some suggestion as to
which loss function to use?
So here, our loss function
would be pairwise.
Yep.
Yeah.
So the proposed answer is
a binary cross entropy.
So can you explicit
that a bit more?
[AUDIO OUT]
Mm-hmm.
OK, so I guess, in that
case, what would it be?
[AUDIO OUT]
Yep.
Yeah, exactly.
So I guess, the--
yes, great answer.
So I guess, your answer is
having some negative log
likelihoods of this
quantity, which is--
so the cross-entropy
can be seen as kind
of a special case of this.
So that we make sure
that we get this part--
so in order to just get that
formulation, which you mentioned
again, I guess, one idea that
we can have is given our data
and given this
formulation that we saw,
the Bradley-Terry one, to
find parameters theta that
maximize the probability of that
data happening, which basically,
leads to what you mentioned.
So here, I'm just going
to write what that means,
so that just we
can be all aligned.
So here, it's-- so let's suppose
you have a preference data sets
of, let's say, winning example
associated with losing example.
So you have a bunch
of pairs like this.
So let's suppose
that these pairs,
they happened independently
of one another.
So what you want is
to find parameters
that somehow maximize
the probability of you
seeing those examples.
So here, what that means is we
want to somehow how maximize
the products of, let's say,
these n preference pairs, which
is the probability of some
output w being better than
some output [? l. ?]
And we saw that with the
Bradley-Terry formulation,
so we have this formulation,
which is basically
the product of [? y1 ?] to n
of these sigma of this reward,
which is basically a
function of the input
prompts and the output.
Like this.
So what I'm doing here
is to just reconstruct
the loss from first principles.
So whenever you see a
product of probabilities,
the first thing you
need to think about is--
yes, log.
Because this can
become very small,
so it can cause instabilities.
So if you take the log, if you
want to maximize the product,
it's the same as
maximizing the log of that.
So if you take the log of that--
so let's suppose I'm taking,
let's say, the log of that.
Let's say I'm taking
the log of that.
So it's basically
equal to the sum
of the log of sigma
of r of the winning
minus the one from the losing.
So we want to maximize that.
But people in ML, they
like to minimize things.
So we're going to take--
like, have a negative in front,
so maximizing plus the sum
of the log is the
same as minimizing
minus the sum of the log.
And so this will be
our loss function.
Does that make sense?
And this is exactly
what you mentioned.
And typically, we
write the expectation.
And this is our loss function.
So our loss function is
minus the expectation
of log of sigma r
and x and y, y hat w
minus the reward of the losing.
Sounds good?
So here, the loss
function is pairwise.
But the reward model, is it
pairwise or is it pointwise?
I guess, do you need a
pair to make a prediction
or do you need just one?
Do you need a pair?
Pair?
Well, that's the
beauty of things.
You don't need a pair, so you're
just training it pairwise,
but it's actually pointwise.
So I think that's
one thing I realize.
I look at this loss, and
this is a [INAUDIBLE]
So you're training
in a pairwise way.
But at the end of the day,
you have a reward model
that takes in one
prompt and its output
and just outputs one number.
And we saw that it
will try to output
a high score for
winning examples
and then a low score
for losing examples.
So this is our reward model.
And I'm looking at the time,
I'm actually not on time,
so I'll just move on.
So typically, here,
what you would need
is a set of data,
which is typically
in the tens of thousands
or maybe even more.
And here, the label would
be the preference rating.
The preference here
should come from humans
if we're talking about RLHF.
And in terms of
model, where you have
a bunch of different choices.
So as we now, models that
are decoder only that
predict the next token
are very popular.
So you could very
well take such an LLM
and just have some
classification heads
at the end of your sentence that
you're taking into consideration
and then use that to
predict the reward.
Or if you remember, we've
also seen encoder only models
in the beginning of the class.
So for instance, BERTs.
You could typically also project
the embedding of the CLS token.
It could very well be an option.
So typically, what
people do nowadays
is take the LLM route because
everything is an LLM these days.
So it's like decoder only.
You just put a
classification head.
And so people have also
come up with benchmarks
to evaluate how
good you're doing.
So we just put a reference
here RewardBench in case
you're interested.
It's a pretty popular one.
But yeah.
So at the end of this,
you get a reward model
that takes in a prompt
and a given response
and gives you a score.
Yep.
[AUDIO OUT]
Exactly.
So the question
is in some tasks,
the human preference would be
something, but another task,
it may be something else.
So typically, those rewards,
they are with respect
to a given dimension.
So they can be, let's
say, is the output useful
or is the outputs
are not friendly?
Is the output safe?
So all of that are
different dimensions,
so they can be
different reward models.
You can also have some
holistic score as well.
But yeah.
So you need to
define a dimension
across which you're
actually quantifying
how good your response is.
So the ones that I mentioned are
the common ones that you'd find.
Another thing that we say
as well, while we're at it,
so human ratings are very
sensitive to the guidelines
that you're also exposing.
So we're not going to
go into details here,
but one important aspect
of human preference data
is to make sure that
the guidelines you're
telling your readers are as
objective as it could get.
I mean, sometimes you cannot
have them be super objective,
but you have, I guess, the
task of just making sure
they're clear enough, so
that your human preferences,
they're not noisy,
because they can be noisy,
but that's also one challenge.
Yeah.
[AUDIO OUT]
So the question is,
is the reward here
a regression or
a classification?
So let's look at the
loss function and here.
So well, it's hard,
I guess, I will
say because the reward
can be something
that can be
interpreted as a score,
but we have a
probabilistic formulation.
So I'll probably frame that
as a classification task
because you have
preference data.
Is it better or worse?
So it's 1 or 0.
But at the end, you
use the rewards.
So it's not, I guess, purely
a classification task because
at the end, you have this.
But one thing to note
is that the scale
that these rewards are
at is typically something
that is scaled itself.
So at inference time, you have
some normalization procedure
that normalizes that
across your batch.
But yeah, I would
probably characterize
the formulation more as a
probabilistic one I would say.
[AUDIO OUT]
Yep.
So the question is, do
we normalize the score?
So there are many different
methods to, I guess,
normalize things.
We typically do.
We typically do normalize.
So I guess if you're in
the regression setting,
you're trying to predict some
score on a given scale, which
you're not doing here.
So it's free form here.
So yeah.
So there is some
rescaling that happens.
Yeah.
You had a question.
[AUDIO OUT]
Yeah.
The question is,
can you tell us more
about what the output
of a reward model is?
So we're going to
see that a bit later,
but you can think of goods
outputs as being, let's say,
1, bad outputs as
being minus 2, minus 3.
So it's basically on the
continuous scale if you want.
We're going to see an
example in a little bit.
So hopefully, this can--
do you have a question?
Perfect.
We're going to see an example.
So hopefully, that
will be clear.
Cool.
So what we did is
train a reward model.
Now, the second step
is to use that reward
model to align our model,
and by model, I mean the LLM.
The LLM that went through the
pre-training stage and the SFT
stage is the model that we want
to align with human preferences.
We're going to do that using
reinforcement learning.
And we're going to do
that using the reward
model that we just constructed.
So the reward model
here is the model
that we obtained in step one.
And it allows us to distinguish
good outputs and bad outputs.
So here is a general recipe of
how you would align your model.
So first, you would take
your prompt as input.
Your LLM will
generate a completion.
So here, a completion means a
full response from the model.
So by the way,
completion, people
use also the term roll-outs.
So it generates a completion,
a rollout, a full response.
And that full response
along with the prompt
goes into the reward model.
So as we saw, the
reward model right now
knows if it's good, if it's bad.
Let's say, right now, it's bad.
So in practice, it does not
generate the thumbs down.
It generates some kind of score.
So if you want minus
2 let's suppose.
So we take that reward
into consideration.
And then what we do is we tune
the LLM with this information.
So it's more
complicated than that.
And we'll see how we
go about doing this.
But this is the general idea.
So just as a reminder,
the reward model
is the model that we
trained as step one.
And it is a model
that is frozen.
We're not training
the reward model.
The reward model
has been trained.
The model that we're
training is the LLM.
So I think that's an
important point to note.
And our goal is to optimize
for higher rewards but then
without going too far
from the initial model.
So I think the optimizing
for higher rewards,
I think, everyone
agrees with me.
But I just said a
second statement,
which is but we don't want to go
too far from the initial model.
So why would that be?
Why would we want to not deviate
too much from the base model?
[AUDIO OUT]
So one suggested answer is
it will catastrophically
forget what it has learned.
Why would that be a problem?
[AUDIO OUT]
Great.
Yeah.
I think it's a
great way to put it.
So the suggested
answer here is you
have all this knowledge in
your initial model, which
is pre-trained and then
instruction tuned or tuned
and you don't want to
move away too much.
This is exactly it.
So that's one reason.
What could be another reason?
So definitely one.
It's very, very good reason.
What could be another reason?
Yeah.
[AUDIO OUT]
Yep.
So overfitting on that data.
So can you tell me more?
[AUDIO OUT]
Yeah.
Great point.
So the second
suggested answer is
you can overfit on data
that is not super clean.
And I will go a bit more into
detail on what that means.
Yeah.
You wanted to add?
[AUDIO OUT]
Yep.
Yeah.
Exactly.
So I guess your two
points are, I guess,
along the same lines, which is
the reward model can be noisy.
So that's exactly it.
So it's a phenomenon that's
called reward hacking, where
if you are trying to optimize
too much for the rewards,
you're basically assuming
that the reward is exactly
quantifying what you want.
But it may not be the
case, because the reward
model itself is imperfect.
So just to make sure that
everyone gets the point,
I'm going to illustrate
that with an example.
So let's suppose that
I'm giving a lecture.
And my objective
is for the lecture
to be as informative
as possible.
So I can take the
choice to have something
that I can quantify to know if
what I'm saying is informative.
So let's suppose if my reward
is how loud the claps are
at the end of the lecture, if
the clapping is a lot or not.
The problem is if I optimize too
much for the volume of clapping
at the end, it may be the
case that if I found out
that you all like jokes
and I start making jokes
and then you clap at the
end, my reward is maximized.
But my objective
is not fulfilled,
which is make the
lecture informative.
So in practice, this
reward hacking phenomenon
is something that
leads your model
to optimize too much on a metric
or a score that is imperfect.
So it can very well
maximize the rewards
but not fulfill what you want.
And this is exactly what the
idea behind reward hacking is.
So yeah.
And another reason by the way.
So it's one reason is
because your base model
is already great.
It knows a lot of things.
Second one is because the
reward model is imperfect.
So you have this reward
hacking phenomenon.
The third reason is also because
you can have some training
instabilities.
Anyways, we have a
bunch of reasons why we
don't want to deviate too much.
And so in this setup, you
typically have more observations
than in the reward model case.
So you have typically at
least 100K observations.
And the label that you get
here is from the reward model.
And so you start with the model
that you obtained after SFT.
So that's the one
that you trained.
And the loss function
will be something
that will try for you to
maximize the rewards but also
to not have you deviate too
much from the base model.
So we're going to see
exactly how we can do that.
But that's the idea of how our
loss function will look like.
It will have these two parts.
Sounds good?
And as we saw, so
we don't want it
to deviate too much because of
reward hacking and instability
and so on.
So in order to do that, you may
have heard a very popular RL
algorithm that's called PPO.
So PPO stands for proximal
policy optimization.
So the reason why
it's named proximal
is because we do
not want our model
to deviate too much
from the base model.
And we're going to
see how we do that.
So this is roughly how our
loss function will look like.
So we'll have a part
that is a reward
model that we want to maximize.
And then some other
part that is around
measuring how far the
distribution of the policy
that we're training is to the
reference model or the base
model.
So here, the reference model
would be your SFT model.
So you have these two parts.
Does the formulation of the
loss roughly make sense so far?
That makes sense?
Cool.
OK.
KL divergence.
So I'm just talking
about KL divergence,
but I don't want to just
assume you know what that is.
So the KL divergence
is some measure.
I don't want to say distance
because distance has
a lot of connotations to it.
It's not a distance,
but it's some measure
of how far two probability
distributions are.
So you take a probability
distribution, let's say, P
and another one
probability distribution
Q. And you compute
this formula, which
is the sum of p i
log of p i over q i.
Just gives you a
number of how distant
or how far these two
probability distributions are.
So you want to
minimize the loss.
So I guess you want to
minimize how far they are.
Does that make sense
that we're using this?
Yeah.
OK.
So just one little question.
So OK.
Is the KL divergence positive or
negative or what can you tell me
about the KL divergence?
Have you seen the-- yeah.
It's positive.
Why is it positive?
[AUDIO OUT]
Yeah.
But why?
So maybe we can come
later but great, great.
I think the result is here,
but I guess I want to why.
Yes.
Exactly.
So yeah, if you use
Jensen's inequality--
because when you look
at this formula, I mean,
luck can take positive
and negative values,
it's not super clear.
But yeah, the way you
prove that it's always
positive or equal to 0 is
with the Jensen's inequality.
And so yes, this
quantity is equal to 0
if and only if P
and Q are equal.
Cool.
So with that, we're going to
go a little bit more in depth
into the loss function.
So I mentioned that
the loss function
tries to maximize for
rewards but also make it
so that the model does not
deviate too much from the base
model.
Well, there is
something that I've
lied a little bit
about too, which
is we don't want to
maximize rewards.
We actually want to maximize
a quantity called advantage.
So what is the advantage?
So you can think
of the advantage
as being how much better
is your output compared
to what you would expect.
So people typically
use advantage
to make the whole process
be, I guess, more stable,
the training more stable.
And we estimate that
advantage with a function
called a value function, which
we will see in a little bit.
Did you have a question?
No, no question.
So we have two quantities.
Right.
We have the reward that we
saw previously how to compute,
which is given a prompt, given
a completion, how good is
this prompt and completion?
And then the value function
is another estimation,
but this estimation is not
at the completion level.
It is actually at
the token level.
So what we're doing here is
we're taking the prompt along
with the partial
generation as input.
And we're trying to estimate
what the reward would
be if we were to continue to
generate the output following
the policy.
So I'm just going to repeat
this one more time because it's
charged in meaning.
The value function is a
token level estimation
of the reward that
takes in a partial input
and predicts the reward.
So that predicts
the reward if you
were to follow the policy
in your generation.
So this value
function is something
you will see in
papers as something
that people have to
train when they do PPO.
And it's typically
because people
need to have this value function
when they compute the advantage
that I mentioned above.
And this value function is
typically trained jointly
with the policy.
So in other terms,
you have your LLM,
which is initialized
as the SFT model, which
generates the prediction.
So what you typically do is also
have some value head that also--
so this time, it's not a
classification problem.
It's a regression problem.
You try to estimate
the final reward
if you were to continue to
generate according to policy.
So this is typically
something that you also
need to train jointly
with the policy.
And I am intentionally
not going too much
into detail as to exactly how
that advantage is formulated.
It is just beyond the
scope of this class.
But in case you're
interested, I would highly
recommend reading this paper,
which is mathematically
involved about the generalized
advantage estimation
methods, which people
typically use for this.
So it's this high dimensional
continuous control
using generalized
advantage estimation paper.
So if you're interested, just
feel free to take a look.
But this is typically the
method that people use
to estimate these advantages.
So now, we're going
to see in a second
where those advantages are used.
But just as a high level,
does that make sense
to everyone what we're
trying to achieve here?
[AUDIO OUT]
Yeah.
So in other words, what we
want is to maximize the rewards
but not deviate too much
from the base model.
But what we want
is to actually find
a way to make the rewards a
bit more relative as to what
you would actually expect.
So you want to
compare the rewards
that you're obtaining with an
average response if you want.
The idea is, OK,
if you are having
a great reward, what would be
the reward in the average case?
And you want to maximize that.
And the reason why people use
these reward minus baseline
is because it reduces the
variance of these estimates,
and it just makes the training
just go faster typically.
So that's why people
use that part.
But in order to compute the
advantage, what people use
is a method called generalized
advantage estimation, which
you can think of
it as a big formula
with some hyper-parameters
that is in the paper below.
That's the general idea.
Cool.
OK.
Looking at the
time, so we're going
to look at two typical
variants of the PPO loss.
The first one is
called PPO-Clip.
So the idea here is to prevent
the updates to our model
from being too large from
one iteration to the next.
So what you have is this
loss formulation, which
is the minimum of the ratio, and
we're going to see what that is,
times the advantage
and some clipping
of that ratio between
two bands, which
we're going to see in a
second, times that advantage.
So before we go
into details, I just
want to call out
a few things that
may seem like it's confusing
because it was confusing to me.
So first of all, that formula
is expressed as L is equal to,
but it's actually not
something we want to minimize,
something that we
want to maximize.
So what people typically
mean by L is loss.
So yeah, just know that
we want to maximize that.
We don't want to minimize.
The second thing is
we're introducing
a term called R of theta.
This is not the reward model.
So typically, people
use R to say the reward.
But here, it's not the reward.
It's actually the ratio in the
probabilities between our policy
and the policy from the
previous step, which is
denoted pi old, pi theta old.
So it quantifies how different
your policy at the current stage
is to your old policy.
So here, when we say, old,
it's not the SFT model.
It's not the SFT model.
It's the model at the previous
iteration during the oral stage,
because here what we want
is for the policy to not
have updates that are too wide.
So far, so good?
Yeah.
[AUDIO OUT]
What is A?
A is our advantage.
So you can think of it as this
complicated formula that's
a function of the reward
and the value function
that just tells you how good
your piece is basically.
So this complicated
formula, we're
just going to see
why it makes sense.
So if the advantage
is positive, it
means that we somehow
want to reinforce
whatever was generated.
And so here, our objective
function will look like this.
So if A is positive,
then this L of CLIP
will look some linear
function as a function of R
because it's R times A.
So it's a linear function
as a function of R.
And then after 1 plus
epsilon, it will just be flat.
So why do we want such
a shape for our graph?
Well, we need to think
again about what R means.
So if A is positive,
meaning it's something
that we want to
reinforce, we typically
want the probability of whatever
happened to be increased.
So we want R to be higher, but
we don't want it to be too high.
So that's why we have
this clipping mechanism.
this clipping here.
We want to, I guess, maximize L.
So we go towards increasing R,
but we don't want to
increase R too much.
So that's the
rationale for this.
But when A is negative, it means
that somehow what we've done
is something that we
don't want to do as much.
So in order to maximize
L, what we want
is to actually decrease the
probability of just generating
what we generated.
So we want R to be smaller
because it also increases L,
but we don't want it
to be much smaller.
We don't want too big
of an update, which
is why we have this
clipping mechanism here.
So in other words, this
super complicated formula
can be just
intuitively explained
with what I just
mentioned, which
is if you have
positive advantages,
you want to reinforce
the fact of generating
this output because this is
something that the model likes.
I mean, by model, I
mean the reward model,
but you don't want it
to update it too much,
which is why you
have this clipping.
And same when the
advantage is less than 0.
I guess you want to down weight
the probability of this output
from happening.
So you want to have
a smaller R, which
is your ratio between the
policy you're training
with respect to the old
one, but you don't want
to be too small
either, again, to not
make too big of an update.
Does this make sense?
Does this roughly make sense?
OK.
Roughly makes sense.
Cool.
I will just recommend just
rereading this formula,
just remembering
what I mentioned.
And hopefully, it will
make a bit more sense.
But yeah, happy to answer any
questions if there are any.
Yeah.
Oh, yeah.
[AUDIO OUT]
So the question is, what
happens where it's not--
it's the same as ReLU.
You will basically
use the same methods.
So yeah, it's the same thing.
Yeah.
[AUDIO OUT]
So great question.
The question is,
why are you using
from the previous iteration
and not the base model?
Because actually, we
don't want just to not
be too far from the base model.
We also want our updates
to be not too extreme
from one iteration to another.
And this is to improve
with stability of training.
So this is just like another
additional constraint we want.
[AUDIO OUT]
Question is are we
considering the base model?
We will consider it.
And I will tell you exactly.
But in this
formulation, we are not.
In this formulation, we are not.
But in the formulation
we're using typically
for LLM based RL, we
are and we will see how.
Yeah.
[AUDIO OUT]
So the question is,
how do you quantify R?
What is R?
What does it mean?
So it's typically the
probability of a token happening
with respect to the inputs.
So you can think of the
probability distribution
that you get at the
output of your LLM.
So you would use that.
Cool.
So this is the first variant
that the PPO paper mentions.
So it's called PPO-Clip.
So the second
variant that we have
is the one that uses
KL divergence, which
is called KL penalty.
And this one is a
function of the ratio
times the advantage
minus the KL divergence
between the old policy, which
is the previous iteration,
and the current iteration.
So you had a great point, which
is why are we using the old?
In fact, old means
previous RL iteration.
But nowadays, people
use the reference.
So it's just a change--
because this paper has
been published in 2017,
where in 2025, LLMs, they came
more into something that was
popular in the 2020s.
So yeah, there's just
been this difference
in what you put there.
So yeah, it's
indeed the reference
that you would typically
put in a KL divergence.
The other thing
that I will say is
that nowadays,
when someone wants
to train a policy using
PPO, they would typically
use the KL divergence,
and they would also maybe
mix it with the clipping
thing with the old iteration.
They will basically mix the two.
There are many
different formulations
of what the loss can be.
So what I'm saying
is not always true.
But this is what
people sometimes do.
They sometimes mix the two.
Cool.
So I talked to you
about PPO and how
it allowed you to
maximize rewards,
maximize advantages by not
making your model deviate
too much from the
base model and also
from the previous iteration.
But the problem is that for
PPO, you need a lot of models.
So you need your policy,
you need your LLM
that you're training.
You also need the value
function, which what I mentioned
is used for the
advantage estimation.
You also need the
reward model of course.
And then you need
the base model.
So the base model is frozen,
so just the SFT model
just to be able to compare
with the current policy.
So it's a lot of models.
So now, the question
that you may ask
is, do you really need to have
all these models to perform
well?
And the answer is maybe
not, maybe but maybe not.
And nowadays, there is
a bunch of other methods
that are becoming more popular.
So you may have heard in GRPO in
the context of reasoning models.
So we will look at GRPO in more
detail next week for lecture 6.
But just know that
there are many variants.
So PPO is just one algorithm
that has been very popular.
And even within PPO,
there's been many variants.
And nowadays, there are
many other RL algorithms
that are being used.
Yeah.
And yeah, if you want to
just anticipate next lecture,
you can also take a look at this
paper from the Deep Seek team.
So Deep Seek Math limits
of mathematical reasoning
in open language models that
introduces the GRPO algorithm.
But if you don't, it's fine.
We're going to talk
about it next week.
So I also want to talk about
some challenges when it
comes to RL-based approaches.
So the first one is you need
to have this two-stage process.
You need to first train
your reward model,
and then you need
to use the reward
model to train your policy.
But the problem is you do
step one, you do step two,
and then you realize, oh,
wait, step one has a problem.
Then you need to
redo everything.
So there is a bunch of
dependencies that can really
make your life harder.
And just the training
recipe is not the simplest.
So that's one downside.
The second downside is about
the number of hyper-parameters
that you need to tune.
So we saw beta from the
KL divergence formulation.
So that's one.
We have epsilon from
the PPO-Clip version.
That's another one.
The generalized
advantage estimation,
we have not seen the formula.
But there's, I think, at
least two hyper-parameters
that I can think of.
Anyways, you have
a bunch of them.
So of course, some
hyper-parameters
perform better than others.
And if you need to
retrain, then, well, you
need to do everything again.
Then you have some
instability challenges.
So you can constrain
your iterations
to not be too wide
to control for that
but sometimes, it's
not sufficient.
So in terms of the
metric that you
can use to monitor
the training, well,
what is the metric
you would use?
So we're trying to maximize
rewards in some sense.
So typically, the
metric that you
would use to monitor
your training
would be the average rewards.
But this is not a great--
I mean, this is a way to
monitor your training,
but this is not the
best way necessarily.
So at least when it came
to pre-training and SFT,
you had this cross entropy
loss that you were monitoring
that was really telling
you how your model was
able to just reproduce
the behavior you
were trying to make it outputs.
But yeah, so this is
another challenge.
And then the other thing
is in the RL world,
in order for you to know which
completion you should not do
and which completion
you should do more,
you need to have some diversity
whenever you generate.
So if during the RL
training loop, every time
you have a prompt, you
generate something,
and then you retry, and you
generate something else that's
too close, well, it's not
great because you're not
exploring the set of
possible completions.
So this is another
challenge you need
to have in mind, which is
you need to force your model
to do some exploration to see,
I guess, what can be good.
And then the last point
is, I mean, a lot of you
were not familiar with RL.
I was not, and it's
not super clear
why we would necessarily
need RL to do this stage.
Also, I will say one thing.
So this RL-based training,
you will hear a lot the term
on policy training.
I just want to tell
you what that means.
So what is different between
this and SFT is during SFT,
we had some prompts
and some response
that we wanted our model
to generate, to mimic.
But here, what we're doing
is at each iteration,
we're asking our model
to generate an output,
and then we're using
how good that output is
to update our model.
So there is a core
difference between the two,
because in here,
what we're doing
is we're asking the model
to generate something,
whereas for SFT,
we're just using
some data that is not
necessarily generated
by our model.
So on policy training
refers to training
that involves the
model generating
from its current policy
and optimizing on that.
And this is in contrast
with off policy training,
which is relying on generations
that are not done by the model
that you're training.
Does this make sense?
Yeah.
So this is a term you
will see a lot, which
is why I'm telling you.
And yeah, so PPO is an
on policy algorithm.
Yeah.
[AUDIO OUT]
So the question is, why don't we
do SFT on this preference data?
Well, SFT, you
tell the model, you
should generate this
given this input,
then you should generate
this given this input.
But you're not telling it about
things you should not generate.
Let's suppose you have something
that you don't want to happen,
unless you rewrite that
into perfect sentence,
there is no way for you in
the traditional SFT framework
to tell your model
to not generate that.
But that being said,
it's a great prompt
because later on in,
let's say, 10 minutes, we
will see a supervised way of
doing what we did with RL.
But yeah, it will be
in about 10 minutes.
But apart from that, does
that roughly make sense?
Yeah.
Perfect.
So in the next few
minutes, we will
see a method that is actually
used more often than not.
And this is for people
who have a reward model
but that don't want to do RL.
So why do you not want to do RL?
Because it's expensive.
You need a lot of models.
So to your point,
it's indeed expensive
because you need
all these models.
And sometimes it's just too
hard to tune that training.
So you have these methods
called best of N or BoN.
And the idea here is to
leverage the reward model
that you obtained in order
to choose the output that you
will return to the user.
So the idea here is
you have a prompt,
and you tell your models,
OK, you actually want
to have several generations.
So you generate, let's
say, 4 times, 5 times.
And what you do is you give a
score to each prompt completion,
and you just return
the best one,
the top rated one, which is
why it's called best of N.
So you have N completions.
You rate all of them, and
you just return the best one.
So you have your prompt.
So our favorite example,
suggest a new activity
I could do with my teddy bear.
You put it into your SFT model.
So you're not training
your SFT model.
It's as is.
And you're just
generating, let's suppose,
three completions.
The first one is a great answer.
The second one is
no, don't spend time
with the teddy bear, which
is not a good answer.
And then the third one, I
think, is also a good one,
take your teddy
bear to a picnic.
You put all of these
into your reward model.
And this is where I
wanted to respond to you,
what is an output
of the reward model?
So it would be a
score like this.
So for instance, the first
one would be a pretty good
completion, so it's 0.8.
The second one is
not good at all.
Let's say, minus 2.
And the third one is, let's
say, so-so, so in between.
So the best of N
method would select
the top rated one,
which is the first one,
and this is the one
that you would return.
So what is one problem
with this approach?
[AUDIO OUT]
So the answer is if the model is
bad, then it's going to be bad.
That's fair.
But I guess if you make enough
completions with, let's say,
a high enough temperature,
you will have some diversity.
So it's a fair point,
which can be a problem,
but let's suppose
it's indeed a problem.
Let's suppose it's
not a problem.
What is another problem
that you may have?
Yep.
[AUDIO OUT]
Yes.
Yes So the answer is you
query the model many times,
which is indeed the problem.
So you're at inference.
What you want is to not spend
a bunch of money and compute.
But here, what you're
doing is complete
your prompt multiple times.
And this is indeed the
main challenge with this.
So you indeed skip
the RL training,
but you're basically pushing
all the work to your inference,
to the inference stage.
And this is just making
everything so super costly.
So when can it be bad?
So if, for instance,
you're in a case where
you need to serve your model to,
let's say, a bunch of traffic,
it may not make sense for you
just from a cost standpoint.
So I would say, before
taking that route,
it may be good to
just assess what
will be your inference traffic,
what would be your training
cost, and determine
that from there.
And yeah, I think
that's pretty much it.
Do we have any
questions on that part?
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
[AUDIO OUT]
That sigmoid would be softmax.
Are you talking about this one?
So in that algorithm, you're
assuming that your reward
model is trained.
So the best of N approach
is you do this training.
So I guess the sigma here
is pairwise because you
trained your model in
a pairwise fashion.
But in the best of
N case, what you do
is you just use your reward
model to score N times,
and you just pick
the highest one.
Yeah.
[AUDIO OUT]
The question is, but what if
all the responses are bad?
This is definitely
a fair concern.
And this is indeed a concern.
So your model needs to be
at least a little bit good.
Yeah.
Exactly.
[AUDIO OUT]
It's a great question.
Do you have any
constraint on the scale?
Well, depending on how
your scaling is done,
you actually don't
care about the scale
as long as you take the best
one, the highest one on.
If you think about it, let's
suppose if you scale it,
let's say, with a normal
score, the highest one
will still stay the highest one.
So in this case, you actually
do not care about the scale.
[AUDIO OUT]
Yes.
You also don't care about that.
But typically, the
scaling matters
when it is coming into play
in a loss function, which
is the case for RL.
And so that's where people
use some scaling mechanism.
That's the part that matters.
Cool.
And with that, I'm going
to give it to Shervin.
Thank you, Afshin.
So for this last part, we're
going to talk about DPO.
But I'm not going to tell
you what DPO means just yet.
We're just going to first
listen to the complaints
we had in the RL world and then
see what we could do about it
and then how have
folks remedied it.
So the first thing
that I'm going
to repeat from
what Afshin covered
is that in the RL formulation
of PPO, you have to carry,
during your loss optimization,
a bunch of model weights.
So when you look at
this loss function,
you have, first, the
policy of the current model
you have to optimize for,
the one of the old model
or the reference model.
And then you have your advantage
which hides the reward model,
as well as the value
function that we discussed.
So all this four,
which is a lot.
And the second thing
is that, let's say,
you go with the
approach of best of N,
you don't do RL, you just
generate multiple times
and then pick the
best completion.
As Afshin mentioned, so you have
this latency and cost issues.
And just for the
sake of thoughts,
for a thought experiment, let's
suppose we had infinite money,
would it be still fine?
So let's suppose you generate
all of these in parallel.
So you would still need to
wait for the maximum time
of the generation of an answer
to give you a resulting answer.
And then if you look at the
distribution of latency,
usually it's some shape that is
not centered on a single point.
And when you look at the
probability distribution
of the max of, let's
say, N answers,
it will tend to be
shifted to the right.
So let's suppose you
have infinite money,
infinite compute, you still
have to wait more than you
would have on a single pass.
Do these concerns make sense?
And OK.
So there comes the question
that someone was asking,
why don't we do
supervision all this time?
And this is the route that
DPO folks have explored.
So DPO stands for direct
preference optimization.
So instead of doing these
expensive two-step process of,
first, finding some reward
model and then iterating
on the model's weights, it
optimizes a single loss function
that directly optimizes
for the model's weight.
And as you can see, there is
no reward involved anymore,
so no R. And you have
a way to formulate
what you care about as a
function of your preference
pairs.
So in that loss
function, all you
have is a bunch of variables
and then the sigmoid functions.
But within the parentheses, you
have the probability of a given
completion to happen.
And you have this
subtraction operation
that compares the probability
of the winning completion
to happen versus the losing one.
So as you can see, it's
a direct expression
with respect to these preference
pairs, which is pretty nice.
And if you look at
it a bit closer,
you will recognize what
afshin just mentioned
regarding Bradley-Terry
formulation because you
have these expected value
of log of a sigmoid.
And then within
that sigmoid, you
have a difference
of terms, where
you can recognize the
equivalent of what
you saw as a reward term.
So I know it's a
lot to see at once.
The formula is not super pretty.
Do you have any questions?
And then we're going to discuss
in a bit what that beta is
and also how we obtain this
formula in the first place.
And one thing I will
mention before going
to that is that the paper is
titled your language model
is secretly a reward model.
And the reason for that is
that the reward placeholder
that you could identify
from this loss function
is expressed as a
function of your policy.
So you don't have
any r's in there.
But when you express the
equivalent of a reward,
you find the expression
of your model directly.
So which is pretty
interesting insights.
OK.
So but now, let's think
together about how we got there
in the first place.
So you recall from
a few slides ago
the PPO objective that we had.
So we wanted to maximize
rewards and minimize
the distance of the
obtained policy with respect
to the reference one,
which is this trade-off
between maximizing rewards
and KL divergence term.
And then you have
this beta coefficient
that appears there that
controls how much you
want to penalize going
further from the base model.
And what this paper did is
that it wrote down this formula
and then solves what would
be the optimal solution.
So it expressed the
optimal policy pi star.
And when you derive
this expression,
so you get it as
a function of R.
So that's another term that
was in the objective function.
And so all these steps
have no extra assumptions.
It's just a bunch of
derivations that was done.
And what you can see
here is this Z term
that stands for a partition
function and that just
normalizes things.
But it's not
something that is new.
It's a function of the terms
that were already in there.
So when you rearrange
these terms,
you can equivalently express r
as a function of this pi star.
So it's just rearranging terms
between these two expressions.
Nothing too fancy.
And then the key part
of what this paper did
is recognize this
term as some reward
and then express it as part of
a Bradley-Terry formulation.
So you remember you had this
probability of a completion,
of a winning completion being
bigger than a losing completion.
And you had this sigmoid of the
difference between the two r's.
So basically, they took
this formulation again,
and they plugged in the
expression they had obtained
for the optimal reward,
which we had seen
was a function of the policy.
So at the end of it,
you plug in things.
You have no more
rewards, just a function
of the other parameters.
So you have this beta and
only the policy in there.
And the last step is the same
one as Afshin was mentioning,
once you have this probability
that you want to maximize,
you can turn it into
a loss function.
And this loss function is
what this paper proposes
to optimize in order
to tune policy weights
in order to align it with
this preference data.
So I simplified a lot the
quite heavy steps of this paper
into these few steps.
Do they make sense?
And the beta that we see
here is the same beta
as we had seen in the PPO
formulation, so typically taken
around 0.1 if you want
some order of magnitude.
So beta is a
hyper-parameter, and all
you want to optimize
for is the policy.
And then the preference pairs,
you have them as inputs.
Makes sense?
OK.
Great.
So now, let's compare
what this method
gives with respect to RLHF.
So RLHF is this two-stage
training process where you first
fit a reward function
and then use it in order
to do the policy update steps.
So Afshin was mentioning
it, it's quite heavy.
We were mentioning
it just before,
you need a lot of
models in memory
and then training
stability is a concern.
You don't have
direct supervision.
You rely on the policy
of the current model
to generate the next updates.
So there is a lot
of complexity in it.
And as opposed to that,
this DPO formulation
gives a supervised way to think
about preference tuning, where
you just take this
preference pairs,
and you directly fit a
loss function on them.
And yeah.
And instead of four
models, you just
need two because you
had this pi of theta
and then a pi ref, which
was your base SFT model,
and you don't need any
other model copies.
So now, you might want to ask
if it's much easier, why is not
everyone just simply using DPO?
So it's not as easy.
In practice, there are some
pros and cons to each method,
and the paper that
is listed below
gives a very interesting study
of the bench-marking differences
and the steps to get there.
So just to get the main
lines, overall, PPO
performs better than DPO.
And one great thing
about DPO, which
is the supervision,
the direct supervision,
comes at the cost of sometimes
fitting something that is not
the exact distribution that the
model has seen as training time.
So this paper talks
about it a bit.
If you train via SFT on the
preference related data,
you could get
better performance.
But this shift in distribution
is a challenge intrinsic to DPO,
because one thing that the
DPO method enables you to have
is just to not worry about
that reward modeling at all
and just get some preference
data set out there.
But the issue with doing so is
exactly that distribution shift.
So you could either
train SFT on it
or donate it yourself
and then rate it.
But that is yet another cost
that you would need to pay.
Great.
And yep.
Any questions?
Yep.
[AUDIO OUT]
So the question is you are
optimizing the parameters
with respect to the base model.
So yes, but it's
not the base model.
It's the current one.
You have a base model that will
stay fixed in the iterations.
And it occurs in
the loss function.
And you're indeed
updating parameters.
And that will be like
the preference tuned one.
Yeah.
So you have two weights, two
set of weights, one frozen, one
that you update.
Yeah.
OK.
Great.
Any other questions?
[AUDIO OUT]
Yes.
So the question is instead
of the reference model,
could you use another
model, another large model?
So I think that's an
interesting point.
I guess that would be
a different algorithm.
And you might lose
a bit the meaning
of what you're trying to do
because this preference tuning
stage is trying to align your
responses to what you prefer.
And you want them to
align with respect
to what you had learned so far.
So if you start from
a different model,
and then you preference
tune a different probability
distribution, you
might be doing things
that might not make as much
sense from a loss standpoint.
But I guess the direction--
I mean, I cannot tell
a blanket answer there.
Maybe it could give
interesting behavior,
but my intuition would tell you
that the point of all of this
is to start from the last
train checkpoint that you had
and then further preference
tune the distribution
of your completions.
So the suggestion was if
you change the reference
model, that could be
seen as another SFT
version of your model.
Yeah.
I guess so.
Great.
And now, my favorite
part of today.
So do you all remember
the completions
we had obtained on
our favorite prompts?
So can I put my teddy
bear in the washer?
So if you remember
last episode, we
had said after
instruction tuning,
the response was, no,
it might get damaged.
Try hand washing it instead.
So does anyone
have any complaints
regarding this answer?
So I can give a hint.
Teddy bears, they indeed
should be hand washed.
So it's factually correct.
But let's suppose it's
factually correct.
What else do you not like?
I mean, could you not
like about this answer?
Yeah.
So the suggestion was it's
asking to try it instead.
And I guess a broader point
is it's a bit too rough.
It doesn't sound super friendly.
And then someone who asks this
question might love teddy bears,
so you might want to tell
them about it in a gentle way.
And this is exactly what
preference tuning stage
is about.
We don't want to
learn new facts.
We want to focus on existing
distribution of completions
and align what the model should
return with respect to what
the human prefers.
So on this intuition, the
preference tunes answer
could be a gentler one.
It's better not to.
Your teddy bear could get hurt.
A gentle hand wash is safer, so
it's conveying the same points
but in a tone that sounds
much better to the ears
of the person who asks.
Great.
Any questions on the DPO part?
Yeah.
[AUDIO OUT]
The question is, what are
the trade offs and then
which one is used in practice?
So I think it all depends on
your compute budget, on how much
you want to worry about
performance versus babysitting
your training process.
PPO, like the RL part, is
very hard to tune right.
It will give the
highest results,
but you might get almost at that
level with much less efforts.
So I guess if you want to get
a quick preference tuning that
is shown to show good results,
but maybe not the best results,
then DPO is your friend.
And if you're an expert
at reinforcement learning,
you know what
you're doing and you
want the every last
bit of performance,
then PPO might be a better way.
Amazing.
And with that,
thank you very much.